"Are Onions Beneficial for Testosterone,
Osteoporosis, Allergies, and Cancer?"
Onions are potentially a
good source of antioxidants,
though interestingly, the
antioxidants are concentrated
in the outer layers immediately
under the papery peel.
Unfortunately, most consumers
discard these most nutrient-rich
outermost layers, thus
losing a valuable part.
Here are some numbers.
Look at that!
More than 10 times
more antioxidants in the
outer layer of white onions,
compared to the core.
You’ll also note that
yellow onions in general
have more antioxidants than white.
And red onions beat
them both, based on three
different antioxidant testing methods.
That’s why I always try to buy red.
Though red onions are
indeed slightly better, yellow
or white onions are no
slouches, containing
considerable levels of
antioxidant activity.
So, nutritious, sure, but
are there any particular
clinical benefits to onion consumption?
There are grammatically
challenged titles like this
in the medical literature purporting
all sorts of miraculous benefits.
But what do they base these claims on?
For example, here’s a review
purporting to have evidence
that testosterone in males
are enhanced by onion,
but the researchers were
talking about studies like this on
the effects of onion juice on
testicular torsion . . . in rats.
Who cares what happens after
a rat testicle is rotated
720 degrees counterclockwise?
(Except, of course, the rat.)
You don’t know what happens
in people until you put
human testes to the test and . . .
onion extracts don’t appear to work.
Okay, what about bone health?
Evidently, older white women
who consumed onions at least
once a day had an overall bone
density that was 5% greater than
individuals who consumed onions
no more than once a month (P < 0.03).
Now 5% might not sound like
a lot, but that improvement in
bone density could potentially
translate into decreasing
their risk of hip fracture
by more than 20%
if indeed, it was cause and effect.
Daily administration of onion did
cause a big bump in bone density.
This opens the possibility for
a low-cost, safe, and effective
nutritional approach
to osteoporosis and—
you guessed it...in the rat.
Another rodent study.
Rats!
But finally, here we go.
Tremendous strides have been made
in treating osteoporosis with
drugs, but they have the potential
for serious adverse side effects,
so scientists have drawn
their attention to natural remedies.
So, let’s randomize people
to drink... onion juice
or placebo onion juice.
I don’t know what sounds worse:
sugary onion juice
or fake sugary onion juice.
And as if drinking onion
juice wasn’t bad enough,
it was all for nothing.
It didn’t even work.
What about the antiallergy
activities of shallots
and any therapeutic effects
on helping allergic runny noses?
Sixteen such patients were
randomized equally into
an antihistamine group or a
group that got antihistamines
plus some capsules containing
dried shallot powder.
And it looked like the
shallot group did better,
but there was actually no
statistically significant difference
in total symptoms
between the two groups;
so, another #OnionFail.
There has to be something
onions can do.
What about testing the effects of
fresh yellow onion consumption
on breast cancer patients to try
to decrease the toxic effects
of a chemotherapy drug
called doxorubicin?
Unfortunately, no significant
benefit was found on decreasing
damage to the liver or heart.
But here we go . . . finally,
a clinical benefit to onions.
The consumption of fresh
yellow onion ameliorates
the high blood sugars and
insulin resistance in breast cancer
patients during doxorubicin-
based chemotherapy.
Doxorubicin isn’t just toxic
to the liver and heart,
but it may also contribute
to insulin resistance.
So, let’s do a randomized, triple-blind,
controlled clinical trial
randomizing patients to
like a whole onion a day
or a third of an onion
a day. What happened?
The high onion group experienced
a significant decrease
in blood sugars and insulin resistance
compared to the low onion group.
They went up in the low onion group
but down in the high onion group.
So, make onions your friend.
What’s the worst that can happen—
a little onion breath and BO?
Probably the least of your worries
if you have cancer on chemotherapy.